Guide to the Martin Shubik Papers, 1947-2009 and undated, bulk 1960-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Correspondence Series, 1955-2007, (38 boxes)
  - Alphabetical Correspondence Subseries, 1961-2005
    - Risks and Financial Instruments, 1990s
    - "S" miscellaneous correspondence, 1980s-1990s
    - Sachnoff, Weaver, 1988
    - Shubik celebration, 1991, (1 of 2 folders)
    - Shubik celebration, 1991, (2 of 2 folders) (Box 44)
    - Siena, 1992
    - Social Systems, 1979
    - Stony Brook, 1985
    - Submissions, 1970s
    - Submissions, 1990s
    - Submissions and talks, 1970s
    - "T" miscellaneous correspondence, 1970s-1980s
    - TEAS Program, 1961
    - Theory of Money and Financial Institutions, 1980s-1990s
    - "U" miscellaneous correspondence, 1980s-1990s
    - "V" miscellaneous correspondence, 1980s
    - "W" miscellaneous correspondence, 1970s-1980s
    - Williams College, 1988-1989
    - Yale information, 1980s (Box 45)
    - Yale inter-office correspondence, 1970s
    - Yale University Press, 1970s-1990s
    - The War Game, 1972-1978, (2 folders)
- Personal Files Series, 1956-2003 and undated, (1 box)
  Files contain an assortment of documents and newspaper articles, some written by Shubik, that reflect several of Shubik's professional concerns, such as political issues around Yale's School of Organization and Management and the topic of the economics of culture and arts. A poem written by Shubik, as well as detailed notes about visits to Stanford University and the RAND corporation office in Washington are included. Files also contain the public announcement of the Lanchester prize awarded to Shubik, a curriculum vitae, quotes of Shubik in public newspapers, and some personal correspondence as well as an essay written by Shubik reflecting on his career as a mathematical institutional economist. Arranged in chronological order.
  - Poem: ENVOI, 1956 (Box 46)
  - Invitation to exhibition of Paintings by Baumol, 1957
  - Price list of Burma handrolled cigars, 1968
  - Notes on Washington trip to RAND office, November 2-7, 1970
  - Shubik quoted in newspaper, 1973
  - Extract from the New Yorker, Three Procedures to the Stable Marriage Problem, November 9, 1974
  - Newspaper article, Prisoner's Dilemma in Personal Computing, November 1979
  - Newspaper article, Master Museum Maker, Barron's, 1987
  - Lanchester Prize Awards, 1984
  - Notes on visit to Stanford University, October 16-17, 1980
  - Newspaper article, Why are they Wrecking the Yale Business School? And how Will it Look on my CV?, 1989
  - Newspaper articles, Yale Business School, 1990
  - Newspaper article, Criteria for a More Effective Presidency, by M. Shubik, 1990
  - Various newspaper articles written by Kass, Douglas A. in Barron's, 1980s and 1990s
  - Reminiscence by Shubik on his career, 1990s
  - From Bosnia to World Crisis, notes by Dujarric, Robert, 1995
  - Who's Who in the 21st Century Questionnaire and Curriculum Vitae, M. Shubik, 2001
  - Interview with Andrew Marshall, The Marshall Plan, 2002
  - Letter to an old friend from Paris, 2003
  - Desirable attributes of a University President, undated
  - Shubik's laws of long-range planning, undated
  - Newspaper article about Yale's School of Organization and Management, undated
- Professional Service Series, 1956-2004 and undated, (7 boxes)
  Contains grant proposals for research projects, memoranda of board meetings,referee reports written by Shubik and others, book contracts and royalty statements, letters of recommendation, professional service agreements, and transcripts of legal testimony or cases in which Shubik was involved. Early files include extensive notes and reports of Shubik on visits and workshops during his professional engagement with General Electric Company, IBM, Mathematica, RAND and others. The series also contains a set of monthly reports written by Shubik to L.M. Hurni from 1956-1960 detailing his research and other professional activities related to GE. Later files contain extensive research notes, conference programs and correspondence centered on Shubik's activities in Latin America and Kenya, the latter in collaboration with the Ford Foundation. Inter-departmental correspondence around the development of the International Security Program at Yale University, annual research reports, and a curriculum vitae of Shubik are also present. The latest files contain a business plan and correspondence on Shubik's project of a Museum of Money and interviews with Shubik. Arranged chronologically.
  - M. L. Hurni, letters, 1956-1960 (Box 46)
    [Shubik's work for General Electric.]
  - Shell strategic planning seminar, (General Electric), 1957
  - Research study, Concepts and Principles of Pricing in General Electric, 1957
  - Letter to the editor from Carlos Garcia Mata about M. Shubik, c. 1959
  - Conference and trip reports in the context of Shubik's engagement with General Electric Company, 1957-1960
  - American Statistical Association, list of committees, etc., 1961
  - Memorandum, deterrence study, 1961
  - Professional service agreement, IBM, 1962
  - Referee reports by M. Shubik, 1960-1963 (Box 47)
  - Clipping, OTAN meeting, July 1, 1964
    Item in French.
  - Police department visit, 1967
  - Research notes, Simulation of Socio-Economic Systems, Ecuador, 1960s, (3 folders)
  - Unidentified referee reports, 1966
  - Referee reports, by M. Shubik, 1957-1967
  - Professional service agreement, RAND, 1969
  - Shell Centre, London, 1969-1972
  - Engagements, research and consultancy activity in Latin America (Chile, Colombia, Brazil), 1960s-1970s, (2 folders)
  - Memorandum, A Note on Extending the Use of FAST-VAL, RAND, 1970
  - Memorandum, Notes on the Gaming Evaluation Project, 1970
  - Proposal, An Integrated Social and Economic Analysis of the United States, 1970
  - Center for War Gaming, 1971
  - Research proposal to NSF, Experimental Gaming in a Time-Sharing Automated Laboratory, 1971
  - Schedule of events, Naval War College, 1971
  - Kenya, Ford Foundation, 1971-1972
  - Research report, Information, Duopoly and Competitive Markets: A Sensitive Analysis, Vienna, 1972
  - Proposal, Models, Simulations, and Games: Theory, Substance, Evaluation and Applications
  - Kenya, Ford Foundation, 1971-1973 (Box 48)
  - Expert witness duties, 1974
  - Shubik's appointment for Knox Professorship at Yale University, 1975
  - Decision Analysis Group at Stanford Research Institute, presentation of models and their methodologies, 1975
  - Consortium research proposal, Laboratory Research Consortium for Controlled Experimentation in the Social and Behavioral Sciences, 1976
  - Improving Regulatory Effectiveness in Federal/State..., Success Factor Evaluation Panel, 1977
  - Nuclear Regulatory Commission, panel on Success Factor Evaluation, 1976-1977, (2 folders)
  - Social Systems, Inc., 1977
  - Memorandum from Task Force Meeting on Gaming, International Institution for Applied Systems Analysis, 1978
  - Expert witness duties, 1979
  - Transcripts of audio recordings, games, game theory, RAND with Brewer, Shubik, Paxson, etc., 1970s
  - Memoranda, research notes on gaming, simulations, RAND with DeWeerd, Marshall, etc., 1970s
  - Nuclear Regulatory Commission, 1970s
  - Proposal, Center for Competitive and Conflict Systems Research, 1970s-1980s
  - Referee reports listing, 1959-1980
  - Correspondence on professional appointment at UC Davis and Stanford University, 1980
  - Expert witness duties and other involvement in legal issues, 1982
  - Center for Competitive and Conflict Systems Research, grant proposals etc., 1982
  - Department of Defense, 1983
  - Legal cases, Shubik v. Empire, Inc., v. Silverman, 1983
  - Frederick W. Lanchester Prize, 1983
  - Office of Naval Research, budgets and contracts, 1983-1984 (Box 49)
  - Grant proposal, Strategic Planning and Risk Analyses, 1984
  - Balinski, Stony Brook, 1984
  - Stony Brook, 1984
  - Office of Naval Research proposal, Economic Warfare and Analytical Methods in Force Mix and Command and Control, 1985
  - Referee reports, 1985-1986
  - Grant paperwork, 1985-1987
  - Reviews and referee reports, 1980-1986
  - Newspaper article with G. Brewer regarding Cape Hatteras Lighthouse, North Carolina, 1987
  - Economic Science Association, 1987
  - Center for Competitive and Conflict Systems Research, report, 1987
  - Project proposal, Quantitative Approaches to Avoiding Accidental War, 1987
  - Guggenheim Museum, 1988
  - Grant proposal, 1988
  - Research proposal, Competitive Enterprise Economics, 1989
  - Williams College Museum of Art, visiting committee membership categories, 1988-1991
  - Report study, National Security and the World Financial System, with Ikle, Fred C., 1980s
  - Center for Competitive and Conflict Systems, research report, 1980s
  - International Security Program at Yale University, grant proposals etc., 1977-1988, (3 folders)
  - Acceptance letter appointing Shubik as adjunct research professor of operations research (Box 50)
  - Provost, Defense, (ISAC Program at Yale), 1989-1990
  - Annual research reports, Yale University, 1989-1999
  - Proposal, Global Security: Quantitative Methodologies for Avoidance of Accidental War, 1989
  - SIAH Institute for Mathematics and Society, proposals etc., 1980s
  - Fred Roberts, 1980s
  - Expert witness duties and legal involvements, 1980s
  - Book contracts, 1980s
  - Proposal, Crisis Stability Games, 1990
  - Gomory, Ralph E., IBM, 1990
  - Proposal for research and teaching by Jerome Braden, 1991
  - Amos, Michael P., criminal case, 1991
  - Consultancy and research activity to the Bureau of the Budget, US Government, 1960s-1990s
  - Defense Economics and Strategic Methodology, research at Yale University, 1980s-1990s
  - Meeting of the members of the Advisory Board of Economic Notes, Siena, 1990
  - Aequs grant, (correspondence), 1991
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, call for nominations, 1992
  - Santa Fe Institute, 1992
  - Hong Kong, 1992 (Box 51)
  - International Security Program, (annual report), 1992-1993
  - Office of the Secretary of Defense, OSD Naval War College, August 1-3, 1993
  - Shubik, Curriculum Vitae, 1993 and 2002
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, nominations correspondence, 1993-1994
  - Royalty statement, 1994
    End "Restricted?"
  - Consultancy activity, RBC project correspondence, proposal etc., 1995
  - Koopman Prize, 1995
  - Grant application, Study of Defense Implications, 1996
  - Guggenheim Forum Program, 1996
  - Referee evaluation, Limits to Science or Limits to Epistemology by Duclauf, S., 1996
  - Report on working group of Geanakoplos, Karatzas, Shubik and Sudderth, 1996
  - Santa Fe Institute Science Board meeting, 1997
  - Barry O'Neill tenure case at Yale, 1998
  - An Exploratorium and Museum of Money and Financial Institutions, 1999
  - Author's permission request by Blaug, Mark, 1999
  - Annual Meeting of Bios Fellows, Santa Fe, July 11-13, 1999
  - Memorandum of Strategic Studies Group of Naval Operations, 1999
  - Defense Economics at Yale, proposals, correspondence, paper drafts, 1990s
  - Annual research reports of M. Shubik, Yale University, 1997-2002
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Commission of the Year, 2000
  - Museum of Money project, 2000
  - Letters of recommendation, 2001
  - Institute of Global Management Studies newsletter, 2001
  - Newspaper article, Los Costos del bioterrorismos, containing analysis by Shubik, 2001
  - In Cash We Trust, New Haven Register, 2002
  - Economic Impact of Terrorism, Yale Newsletter, 2002
  - Sardine as Metaphor, Yale Newsletter, 2002
  - The Museum of Money and Financial Institutions, business plan, 2002
  - Science Advisory Board, 2002, (2 folders)
  - The Econometric Society, election of officers and council, 2002
  - Annual research report of M. Shubik, Yale University, 2003-2004
  - Newspaper article regarding the Tax History Museum, Nixon's Tax Return, A Cyberspace Treasure, New York Times, 2004 (Box 52)
  - Santa Fe Institute 2006 Annual Report
  - Q2, interview, Can We Manage without Markets, 2007
  - Journal of Mathematical Economics, special section in honor of M. Shubik, 2009
  - Interviews with Shubik, undated
  - El Periódico de la Universidad, undated
  - Recommendations, undated
  - Synopsis of Pollack meeting, undated
- Teaching Materials Series, 1960s-2001 and undated, bulk 1970s-1990s, (3 boxes)
  Contains an array of course materials such as lecture notes, syllabi, reading lists, teaching evaluations and student term papers from Shubik's courses at Yale University, some of which were co-taught with other faculty. Also present is some correspondence with PhD students and their thesis prospectuses. Arranged chronologically.
  - Lecture series notes, 1961, (2 folders) (Box 53)
  - PhD thesis readings, 1960s-1970s
  - Lectures in microeconomics, University of Chile, 1965
    Contents in Spanish
  - Seminars and other materials, Chile, [1965]
  - List of participants in microeconomics lecture, 1971-1972
  - Lecture notes, Money and Financial Institutions, with Whitman, M.S., 1972, (3 folders)
  - Course materials, Money and Financial Institutions, 1973
  - Course materials, Seminar of Industrial Structure and Market Behavior, 1969-1970 (Box 54)
  - Course materials, Gaming and its Applications, 1973-1975
  - Course, Gaming and its Applications, 1974-1975
  - Course, Material Money and Financial Institutions, 1976
  - Course, Material Money and Financial Institutions, 1976
  - Course materials, Strategic Planning, Modeling and Economics, 1981
  - Lecture notes, On Modeling in Political Economy, 1981
  - Course materials, Securities Analysis and Portfolio Management, 1984-1985, (4 folders)
  - International Security Studies and Arms Control at Yale University, 1986-1995
  - Course evaluations, Risk and Organization, 1987
  - Course materials, Risk and Organization, 1987
  - Seminar materials, Theory and History of Money and Financial Institutions, 1987-1988
  - Course materials, Defense Analysis Methodology, 1988
  - Course materials, Games Theory in the Social Sciences, 1988
  - Course materials, The Management and Economics of Culture, 1990
  - Course materials, The Management and Economics of Culture, 1991
  - Course materials, Theory of Money and Financial Institutions, 1991
  - Correspondence and course materials, Economics and Management of Culture, 1992 (Box 55)
  - Course materials, Financial Institutions, 1993
  - Course materials, Derivatives and Financial Engineering, 1994
  - Evaluations, Derivatives and Financial Engineering, 1994
  - Teaching list, Yale University Economics Department, 1994
  - Course evaluations, 1994
  - Course evaluations, Theory and History of Money and Financial Institutions, 1998
  - Teaching schedule, Shubik, 1998
  - Course evaluations, History of Money, 2001
  - Thesis abstract, Sahi, Siddhartha, undated
- Writings and Research Series, 1951-2009 and undated, (59 boxes)
  Arranged into two subseries, Writings by Shubik and Writings by Others, with the majority of the material falling under the first division. Writings by Shubik is further subdivided into four subseries, organized alphabetically: Articles; Books; Other Papers; and Research Files. Further description follows each subgroup's entry.
  - Writings by Shubik Subseries, 1952-2008 and undated, (59 boxes)
    Subseries is divided into two parts, beginning with Shubik's scholarly articles. A prolific author, Martin Shubik wrote hundreds of articles from the 1950s through the 2000s, most of which are represented in this subseries. Second is a subseries housing the many Cowles Foundation Papers written by Shubik, often co-authored by other scholars and economists.
    - Articles by Shubik, 1952-2008 and undated, (18 boxes)
      - Reprints, 1952-2008, (9 boxes)
        Shubik used a sequential numbering system to identify his writings, and his arrangement has been retained here. The numbers given represent individual titles, which can be identified in a paper list of titles available in the collection control files, in the first box, or on the web. In addition to the original reprint, parentheses indicate accompanying materials such as drafts, correspondence, notes, and reviews. Some publications are not present in the collection.
        - Nos. 1-18 (Box 56)
        - No. 19 (drafts, notes)
        - Nos. 20-21
        - No. 22 (referee report)
        - Nos. 23-34
        - No. 39 (draft)
        - Nos. 40-43
        - No. 45 (typed manuscript with revisions)
        - Nos. 46-48
        - No. 49 (correspondence)
        - Nos. 50-58
        - No. 59 (notes, drafts)
        - Nos. 61-62
        - No. 64 (galley, no reprint)
        - Nos. 66-67 (Box 57)
        - No. 68 (draft)
        - Nos. 70-71
        - No. 72 (draft)
        - No. 73
        - No. 74 (draft)
        - No. 75 (draft)
        - Nos. 76-90
        - No. 91 (draft)
        - Nos. 92-94
        - No. 95 (draft)
        - Nos. 96-105
        - No. 106 (draft, typed manuscript), (2 folders)
        - Nos. 107-119
        - No. 120
        - Nos. 121-131 (Box 58)
        - No. 132 (notes, drafts, research, CFDP, no reprint)
        - Nos. 134-137
        - No. 138 (working paper)
        - Nos. 139-150
        - No. 151 (draft)
        - Nos. 152-159
        - No. 160 (typed manuscript)
        - No. 161 (typed manuscript)
        - Nos. 163-164
        - No. 165 (handwritten draft, photocopy of working paper, no reprint)
        - No. 166 (typed manuscript)
        - No. 167
        - No. 168 (handwritten draft)
        - No. 169
        - No. 170 (galley)
        - Nos. 171-176
        - No. 179 (working paper, no reprint) (Box 59)
        - No. 180 (drafts, notes, no reprint)
        - No. 183
        - No. 184 (working paper, no reprint)
        - No. 185 (typed manuscript, no reprint)
        - Nos. 188-189
        - No. 190 (drafts, no reprint)
        - No. 191
        - No. 193 (draft, no reprint)
        - No. 195 (draft)
        - No. 197 (preliminary paper)
        - No. 199 (handwritten draft, book reviews, correspondence, no reprint)
        - No. 200
        - No. 202 (galley)
        - No. 206 (written draft, typed manuscript, correspondence), (2 folders)
        - Nos. 207-209
        - No. 210 (revisions, correspondence, working paper, no reprint)
        - No. 212 (typed manuscript, no reprint)
        - No. 213 (typed manuscript)
        - No. 214 (drafts, working paper) (Box 60)
        - No. 215
        - No. 217 (revised proof, correspondence)
        - No. 219
        - No. 220 (CFDP working paper, Institute for Decision Sciences working paper, correspondence, no reprint)
        - No. 221 (working paper)
        - No. 222
        - No. 223 (typed draft with revision, correspondence
        - No. 224 (proof)
        - No. 225 (proof, correspondence, draft)
        - No. 226 (no reprint)
        - No. 227
        - No. 228 (draft, correspondence, working paper)
        - No. 229 (draft, correspondence, no reprint)
        - No. 230 (typed manuscript, correspondence, report)
        - No. 231 (working paper, drafts, notes)
        - No. 233 (drafts, discussion paper) (Box 61)
        - No. 234 (working paper)
        - No. 235 (revised proof, notes, drafts, correspondence), (4 folders)
        - No. 236
        - No. 238 (working paper)
        - No. 239 (working report, drafts, correspondence), (3 folders)
        - No. 240 (working paper, notes, correspondence), (1 folder)
        - No. 240 (working paper, notes, correspondence), (2 folders) (Box 62)
        - No. 241 (typed manuscript, draft, correspondence, no reprint), (2 folders)
        - No. 243 (working paper, draft)
        - No. 244 (working paper, manuscripts, drafts, research notes, correspondence, no reprint), (2 folders)
        - No. 245 (manuscript, notes, drafts, revised draft, correspondence, no reprint), (3 folders)
        - No. 245 (manuscript, notes, drafts, revised draft, correspondence, no reprint), (1 folder) (Box 63)
        - No. 246 (final draft, correspondence, no reprint)
        - No. 247 (typed manuscript, draft, correspondence)
        - No. 249 and No. 255 (typed manuscript, drafts, revisions, no reprint)
        - No. 250 (typed manuscript, student report, no reprint)
        - No. 251 (typed manuscript)
        - No. 254 (drafts, research notes, correspondence, no reprint)
        - No. 255 (typed manuscript, no reprint)
        - No. 256 (typed manuscript, drafts, no reprint), (2 folders)
        - No. 260 (typed manuscript, working paper)
        - No. 266 (typed manuscript, typed manuscript with revisions, no reprint)
        - No. 266 (typed manuscript, no reprint) (Box 64)
        - No. 267
        - No. 268
        - No. 269 (galley, no reprint)
        - No. 271 (working draft, correspondence, no reprint)
        - No. 273
        - No. 274 (drafts, CFDP, correspondence, no reprint), (2 folders)
        - No. 277 (working paper, no reprint)
        - No. 279 (proof, no reprint)
        - No. 281
        - No. 282 (typed manuscript, no reprint)
        - No. 287
        - No. 288 (referee report)
        - No. 290
        - No. 291 (correspondence)
        - Nos. 293-294
        - Nos. 295-306
      - Cowles Foundation Reports (CFR), 1960-2005, (9 boxes)
        Includes Cowles Foundation Discussion Papers (CFDP) and Cowles Foundation Reports (CFR) stemming from the Cowles Foundation for Research in Economics at Yale University. Shubik used a sequential numbering system to identify his writings, and the papers are arranged by this system. The numbers given represent individual titles, which can be identified in a paper list of titles in the first box, or online on Shubik's web site. In addition to the original report, accompanying materials such as drafts and revisions, correspondence, and notes are often included. Some reports are not present in the collection.
        - Cowles Foundation Discussion Paper, Nos. 100-104 (Box 65)
        - CFDP No. 105 (typed draft)
        - CFDP Nos. 107-167
        - CFDP No. 170 (typed draft)
        - CFDP Nos. 180-208
        - CFDP Nos. 217-230
        - CFDP No. 233 (referee report)
        - CFDP Nos. 236-240
        - CFDP No. 247 (early draft, revisions)
        - CFDP No. 249 (Box 66)
        - CFDP No. 270 (referee report)
        - CFDP Nos. 274-289
        - CFDP Nos. 316-330
        - CFDP No. 334 (revisions, notes)
        - CFDP Nos. 331-338
        - CFDP Nos. 347-364
        - CFDP Nos. 365-374
        - CFDP Nos. 377-410R
        - CFDP Nos. 414-429 (Box 67)
        - CFDP Nos. 431-448
        - CFDP Nos. 454-460R
        - CFDP Nos. 462-476
        - CFDP Nos. 478-484
        - CFDP Nos. 507-525 (Box 68)
        - CFDP No. 557 (correspondence, referee reports)
        - CFDP Nos. 559-619
        - CFDP No.627 (working draft, correspondence), 2 folders
        - CFDP Nos. 634R-706
        - CFDP Nos. 712-733
        - CFDP No. 744 (handwritten drafts)
        - CFDP Nos. 747R-787 (Box 69)
        - CFDP No. 789 (typed draft)
        - CFDP Nos. 804-814
        - CFDP No. 814R (drafts, handwritten drafts)
        - CFDP Nos. 841-871
        - CFDP No. 879
        - CFDP Nos. 879R (early manuscript)
        - CFDP No. 891 (typed manuscript)
        - CFDP Nos. 895-964
        - CFDP Nos. 996-1037 (Box 70)
        - CFDP No. 1040 (notes, correspondence)
        - CFDP No. 1043
        - CFDP No. 1046 (drafts, correspondence)
        - CFDP Nos. 1056-1076
        - CFDP No. 1050 (notes, drafts)
        - CFDP No. 1088 and No. 1095 (correspondence, summary), (2 folders)
        - CFDP No. 1089 and No. 1088 (research)
        - CFDP No. 1094 (summary)
        - CFDP No. 1099 (revised draft, correspondence)
        - CFDP Nos. 1112-1132
        - CFDP No. 1156 (Santa Fe Working Paper, draft with notes, revised manuscript, early draft), (5 folders) (Box 71)
        - CFDP Nos. 1174-1184